<skill title="Surgical Debugging Methodology" 
       description="A scientific, iterative framework for diagnosing and fixing complex bugs using strategic instrumentation and hypothesis validation." 
       category="tools/debugging" 
       id="surgical-debugging"
       language="markdown">
<![CDATA[
# 🔬 Surgical Debugging Methodology

When facing a difficult task or an elusive bug, do not guess. Follow this iterative, observation-driven protocol.

## 1. The Golden Rule: "Look, Don't Assume"
Most debugging time is wasted assuming a variable has a certain value or a function is being called. 
- **Validate Everything**: Use tools to inspect the state.
- **Isolate the Failure**: Narrow the search area until you find the exact line where reality deviates from expectation.

## 2. Phase 1: Reproduction
Before attempting a fix, you MUST be able to see the failure.
- If the code crashes, ensure you can trigger the crash.
- If the output is wrong, define exactly what "wrong" looks like compared to "right".

## 3. Phase 2: Strategic Instrumentation (The Print Loop)
If you cannot use an interactive debugger, use the **Print Loop**. Insert `print()` statements to create a "stream of consciousness" for the program.

### Where to place prints:
- **Function Entry/Exit**: `print(f"> Entering [func_name] with args: {args}")`
- **Branching Points**: Inside `if/else` blocks to see which path is actually taken.
- **Data Transformations**: Before and after complex logic or API calls.
- **Loop Iterations**: Use markers for high-frequency loops: `print(f"--- Loop Index {i} | State: {state} ---")`

### Formatting for clarity:
- **Add Context**: Never print a raw variable. Always label it: `print(f"DEBUG [UserAuth]: token_val={token}")`.
- **Type Checking**: If behavior is weird, print the type: `print(f"DEBUG: var={var} type={type(var)}")`.
- **Breadcrumbs**: Use unique strings to find your place in the logs: `print("!!! REACHED CHECKPOINT B !!!")`.

## 4. Phase 3: Observe & Hypothesize
Run the code and analyze the output.
1. **Trace the flow**: Did the program reach your checkpoints in the order you expected?
2. **Inspect the data**: At what point did a variable become `None`, `NaN`, or an empty string?
3. **Form a Hypothesis**: "The loop fails at index 5 because the list is shorter than expected."

## 5. Phase 4: The Fix & Verify Loop
1. **Apply the surgical fix**: Change only what is necessary to validate your hypothesis.
2. **Verify**: Run the code again. **The prints must stay in place** during verification to prove the logic is now correct.
3. **Check for regressions**: Ensure your fix didn't break a different part of the sequence.

## 6. Phase 5: Cleanup
Once the bug is confirmed fixed and verified:
- Remove all debugging `print()` statements.
- Replace critical diagnostic prints with proper `logger.debug()` or `logger.info()` calls if the information is valuable for production.
- Document the root cause in the code if the logic remains non-obvious.

## 🚀 Summary Checklist for the AI:
- [ ] Can I reproduce the error?
- [ ] Have I added descriptive prints at the boundaries of the suspected logic?
- [ ] Did I verify the variable types and values at runtime?
- [ ] Does my fix resolve the issue in the logs without breaking the flow?
- [ ] Did I clean up my "scaffolding" (prints) after the fix?
]]>
</skill>